How can taking on the precept of
non-entertainment help reveal the subtler and more
help reveal the subtler and more
fundamental
um tendency towards distraction?
Well, by taking on the precepts, that's how it
by taking on the precepts, that's how it
would reveal it.
But then how do you How do you draw that
line for yourself when you you're kind
of comfortable within that precept, but
the tendency to distraction still
exists? So, you mean you're not giving in to the
So, you mean you're not giving in to the
entertainment
in a sense of breaking the precept,
but are still distracting yourself? Yes.
Or contrasting that with things that
take up your time and attention, and you
might kind of just because they seem
like they would be distraction.
If you're not so sure where to draw the
difference between that intentional
distraction and things that just happen
to take time, but are not necessarily
>> to do. Yeah.
Well, that's the difference.
Did you initiate it, or do you just have
to do it?
And how far Like when you initiate
something, just ask,
just ask,
where is this coming from?
Like how distracting it will be, and
what if I
What if I don't do it?
Is the mind resisting that idea?
Then you know that there is some impulse
behind me needing to do something.
But it's not really I don't know, it's
not really a brain science, like
you have to
say no,
see whether the mind resists, sometimes
say yes. It's all within the precepts.
See whether the mind becomes completely
unaware of itself when you're
distracted, and then other things come up, and then
and then other things come up, and then
recognize, "Aha, well, last time when I
did what I had to do,
next 4 hours I was completely
distracted, and then the evening
sensuality came and ill will came cuz
the mind was completely switched off. So
next time when I have to do something
well, I'll be more careful and don't go
that far internally.
Keep at least some
degree of self-awareness in regard to
things even while I'm doing them.
Yeah, I could sounds familiar like this
uh
you maybe
some time of the day
you know you you're bored.
Mhm. There's suffering there
in the background.
And uh
Uh let me just I mean read the sūtras.
Let me go into this and he starts
reading the sūtras because it's kind of
you know, that's okay. Mhm. But
and you do that for 4 hours, but you you
started because you were bored. Mhm. You
start So you you you're just carrying
that whole
um
energy with you. So it's you you're
developing that resistance to boredom
Mhm. by by studying the Dhamma.
By studying the sūtras and so on. So at
the end of it after 4 hours
you're still as agitated as ever. And
I think it's more like the question of
duration there rather than because yeah,
reading the sūtras
even if you do it for the distracting
purposes, if you're actually reading
them, they are pointing back to things
you're trying to distract yourself from.
Yeah. So it can kind of help you. Mhm.
But yes, if you are doing it for 4 or 5
hours means okay, you're doing it with
like a even more diminished
self-awareness and I think that will be
the problem.
In other words, spend 4 hours whereby
you haven't acknowledged the fact that
you are distracting yourself.
As opposed to you you start with a
distraction, but out in you become way
too self-aware cuz you're actually
reading the sūtras and thinking about
those things and the distraction
disappeared. The motivation disappeared.
To distract yourself.
So that's fine, but again, are you doing
the suttas? Are you reading the suttas
even through the desire of distraction,
but are you still actually searching for
the meaning?
Or are you just, as I said, collecting
knowledge, uh scholastic information and all the
uh scholastic information and all the
other kind of secondary things for which
you could go for 10-15 hours
of \ and \ study and not
get at a step closer to the actual
meaning of those phenomena that are
visible here and now while you're doing
it.
I suppose also you know, okay, I'm
bored.
Kind of restless or whatever, so I'm
I'm wanting to do something, so but I'm
reading suttas, but then you always you
always you're not acting out, you're not
going for sensual sensual things.
>> [clears throat]
>> Uh
and you're still aware of that mind
being bored. Yeah. So I'm not really
cultivating craving there. Yeah.
It's just like I'm whatever is covering
up that state of mind, that's the wrong
thing. Whatever is leaving it um seen, visible,
Whatever is leaving it um seen, visible,
no matter even [clears throat] if it's
bored or angry, Mhm. lustful, as long as
that's not covered up.
Well, yeah, that's that's the
motivation. That like if you uncover
your motivation,
then things are clear. It doesn't matter
what state of mind it is.
Yeah.
But it's not like, oh, I shouldn't be
reading the suttas now
because it's everything is a
distraction. I must just stay with this.
Like you might factually still need to
read the suttas.
You need the right reminders, the right
context, the new angles to make you
pierce through these
obtuse kind of phenomena and so on.
So even if you do it out of desire, even
if you do it out of restlessness,
yeah, it it can go only so far.
The suttas can't point you back into
centrality or will as other aspects of
entertainment or careless pointless work
can.
But yes, even that fundamentally the
time will come when you recognize,
"Okay, but even this now needs to be
abandoned." But don't start abandoning
that before the major things are still
not even trained in.
"Oh, I must stop reading the suttas cuz
everything is a desire."
And don't read the suttas, remain
equally trapped by the desire, manage to
hold the floodgates for a while, but
without a deeper understanding and
insight and knowledge, you will go back
to those things like you were like you
did before.
So, again, purification of the gold. You
don't be You're not removing microscopic
impurities while it's still like
indistinguishable from mud.
So, if the coarse entertainment is not
followed,
you might catch yourself doing this
project or that project. But again, if
there is self-awareness, you will put a
lid on it. You're like, "Okay, let's
let's not go too far. Let's
And suddenly you won't feel justified in
it. I think that's also the major aspect
of that.
When people think, "Okay, I'm not
breaking the precept of entertainment,
therefore any project
in the monastery or Dhamma related is
justifiable in and of itself and I don't
have to think about it and I can just
commit to it and do it
and sort of coast off it.
Um and that's like No, that's that's
it's it's as as ignorant as as if this
as the stuff you were doing before.
So, you will be doing that to some
degree. You'll be catching yourself in
doing it, but then if you're not
justifying it,
that's already containing it. That's
already putting on That's already
limiting it how far your
distraction within keeping the
entertainment precepts can go.
So, yes, you catch yourself reading the
suttas 1 day, 2 days, 5 days, doesn't
matter. But as I said, there is always the the
But as I said, there is always the the
broader recognition of Okay, yeah.
You know, the pressure of boredom or
distraction was too strong. I couldn't
say no. I didn't go to entertainment. I
did something else. That's fine. I'm not
justifying it. I'm not hiding
responsibility. I'm keeping an eye on my mind while I'm
I'm keeping an eye on my mind while I'm
doing it.
So that becomes even more familiar. So
that next time, like I don't have to do
it for those reasons. Or gradually.
Um
And that's how you sort of like like
like um as I said, gradually contain the
animal more and more and more.
Um through recognition how far you need
to go.
But through simultaneously knowing that
well, you don't start at the end.
Like oh, this is how far I need to go in
terms of containing the animal, but I
can't start there. I mustn't forget that
and start where I need to start.
Which is the coarsest entertainment.
Absolutely pointless
projects that just
um
kind of
take over your mind with
inspiration and everything else and you
don't think about anything else cuz you
have stuff to do.
Um
you minimize that. Then if it's your
sutta study, reading the suttas, asking
questions, you could say oh, I'm doing
that for because I'm restless, fine.
Wait until that becomes the most coarse
form of obstacle and then okay, now I'll
say no to that.
In the meantime, keep an eye on it. Do
not ignore it. Certainly don't
absolve yourself from it. But don't
think like I'll just stop that while all
the other things just floating around
unchecked.